טוב, Tov,
today's דף daf is מ"ד mem daled and we start the fourth
פרק, perek, הזהב. Hazahav. It's one of the understood to be one
of the more difficult פרקים prakim in ש"ס, Shas, but don't worry,
it's not as difficult as the one that's coming after it.
So much for optimism. Exactly. Okay, anyway, so let's take a look.
Actually, though, recent events of when, exactly, oh my god. Anyway, I
would say though that the beginning at least is pretty straightforward. So
we get at least we get off to a good start. Let's
take a look.
Although, you know, it is interesting how the משנה, mishna, how the
מסכת masechet is shifting. You know, you had two פרקים prakim about
מציעא, Metzia, one about being a שומר, Shomer, although it really dealt
with the special cases without ever dealing with laying down the basic
principles of שומרים, Shomrim, which is strange. And now we deal once
more with what has to do with, like, buying and transactions, money
transactions.
Next, the fifth פרק perek is going to do with lending money
and ריבית. Ribbis. This פרק perek has to do with, not exactly
lending money, although it's interesting, it starts to talk about exchanging money
for money, but what it's really, at least, you know, the beginning
very much is focusing on is about קניינים, kinyanim, about purchasing things.
Now to some degree we dealt with קניינים kinyanim in קידושין, Kiddushin,
if you remember, talked about like, you know, when do you do
הגבהה, hagbah, when do you do משיכה, meshichah, and so on. But
this gets to not the question about like, how do you, what
act of קניין kinyan do you do on a particular object, but
what, how in הלכה Halacha do you conceptualize what is defined as
money and what is defined as object? So let's take a look
at that because the הלכה Halacha is, if you sell me something,
right, and it's chattel, it's מטלטלין, metaltelin, it's not קרקע, karka, the
sale is finalized when I take possession of the object, whether that's
a הגבהה hagbah or a משיכה, meshichah, lifting it up, drawing it
to me. So whether I've paid you the money for it or
not, that doesn't finalize the sale. So what finalizes the sale is
taking possession of the object. So normally it's very clear what's the
object and what's money. Okay, you know, the object, you know, we
know what cash is and you know what money is, that's the
coins that are used, etc., and the price in which things are
given are quoted in the price of money, and the object is
everything else. But let's say, but let's say you are exchanging money.
Now, you know, the way we would think about exchanging money is
I'm exchanging, I don't know, dollars for euros, dollars for shekels. So
when is the קניין kinyan finalized? When the other guy takes the
dollars or when I take the shekel? All right, so that's one
type of case, literally different types of currency in different places. I
don't think the גמרא Gemara deals with that. But what the גמרא
Gemara deals with is exchanging money within one country. Okay, now if
I'm going to give, you know, here's a hundred, please give me
it in singles, okay? So what's the money and what's the object?
Now, you could say they're both money, but then that doesn't help
because there's no קניין kinyan that's done, right? Because the קניין kinyan
only takes place when the object is taken possession of, not when
the money switches hands. You could argue I guess that in that
scenario they're both objects, but that's a little bizarre. I mean, you
know, presumably and, you know, that is one of them or both
of them really is functioning as money. So that leads to the
interesting point of the first משנה, mishna, which is trying to identify
what is defined as money and what is defined as object within
the world of currency. So let's take a look now at the
first משנה. mishna. הזהב קונה את הכסף הכסף אינו קונה את הזהב.
Hazahav koneh es hakesef, hakesef eino koneh es hazahav. So gold coins
buy silver. Now again what's complicated here is when I tell you
gold buys silver, you think of the first thing I'm saying, the
thing that buys, as the money, right? It buys the object. But
that's, you have to sort of reverse your way of thinking with
this משנה mishna because what it means is when you take possession
of the gold, that causes the other side to own the silver.
So the gold is the object. Okay, meaning the paradigm statement is,
so
I'm giving you my gold for silver, you take the gold and
I get the silver.
Exactly. So it's מטלטלין metaltelin are קונין konin
קונים konim whatever את הכסף. es hakesef. Okay, meaning that's the basic
point, right? The object takes, you know, transfers ownership, you know, takes
acquisition of or whatever changes ownership of the money. Is it קונים
konim or קונה? koneh?
קונה, koneh, קונה, koneh, meaning anyway,
right, right, same word, הזהב קונה את הכסף. hazahav koneh es hakesef.
Look later in the משנה. mishna.
Later in the משנה mishna it says כל המטלטלין קונים
זה את זה,
kol hametaltelin
konim
zeh es zeh, המטלטלין קונין את המטבע. hametaltelin konin es hamatbeah. Okay,
it's המטבע. hamatbeah. Where is he going there? But you... Think about
it the opposite way. Yeah, so yeah, meaning so that's funny, right,
you would say, you would say coins buy the cattle, you
wouldn't say the cattle buys the coins. Okay, so you have to
sort of reverse the way you're thinking
about it. What it means is is that when it says
X is קונה koneh Y,
it means X is
the object and Y is the money.
So the focus is to be doing the act of possession on
X, and when you do the act of possession on X, then
the other side owes the money. Okay, so הזהב קונה את הכסף
hazahav koneh et hakessef means if you're switching gold coins for silver
coins, the money in this exchange is the silver coins. Okay, and
if the when you take possession of the gold coins, then the
other side owes then the silver coins are are owed. הכסף אינו
קונה את הזהב, hakessef eino koneh et hazahav, but if one side
takes possession of the silver coins, the gold is not yet owed,
the the sale is not yet final. Okay, so the first thing
mentioned in these in this phrase when X is קונה koneh Y,
X is the object, Y is the money. הנחושת קונה את הכסף,
hanechoshet koneh et hakessef, so copper coins, right, it's copper, you know,
it's gold, silver, copper. Copper coins are קונה koneh silver coins. Copper
is the object and silver is the money. והכסף אינו קונה את
הנחושת, vehakessef eino koneh et hanechoshet, but silver coins are not קונה
koneh copper coins. Okay, one minute. מעות רעות קונות את היפות, maot
raot konot et hayafot, bad money, which either means that it's completely
been you know sort of de-invalidated, money after the, you know, after
the civil after the Civil War, right, the money from the southern
states or whatever, Confederate money after the Civil War. That's what רש"י
Rashi says. תוספות Tosafot said that would be too obvious. What bad
money here means is it's money that basically is not everybody will
accept, you know, it's like damaged, it's like, you know, when אברהם
Avraham buys, you know, עפרון Efron it says עובר לסוחר, over lassocher,
right, which means that like anybody would accept their money, you know,
it's got like a it's got a stamp on it, it's clear
what its weight is, you know, and so on, whereas some sometimes
the money, either because it's a currency that is only accepted like
locally, it's not a currency that's accepted, you know, you know, outside
of your locale, outside of your town, or because the actual coins
themselves are somewhat damaged. You know, you ever try to sometimes pay
something with like a crumpled up, really really old dollar bill? The
storekeeper, like, he probably is legally required to accept it. He is,
but in other countries they don't accept it. Right, so you could
say, I'm not accepting this, this is a, you know, this is
a whatever, this is totally crumpled up. Even in a machine, you
know, like the machine won't accept a bad one it'll come popping
out. Yeah, that's because the machines can't do a good scan of
it, that's not because it's for a different reason. Anyway, okay. What
about stolen money? We're not dealing with stolen, that's not relevant here.
So, okay, so anyway, so if it's bad money, no, but you
still want to buy, you're not buying necessarily at the same rate,
right? I'll give you, I'll give you, for this clean fresh hundred
dollar bill, I'll buy a hundred and two crumpled up... It's not
crumpled, it's like invalidated. Oh, so then you melt it down. We're
dealing with stuff that that's made of the precious, you know, that
has precious the precious metal content. Okay, so if you've got money
that's that's valid or more valid, like, you know, more widely accepted
and money that's less so, that's in bad shape and only accepted
under extreme situations, so clearly it doesn't matter which is the gold
and which is the silver, the one that everybody recognizes as money
is the money, and the other thing is the object. Okay, isn't
it the same for the first part, right, that's if, you know,
because that's because you want to give A and get B, זהב
zahav and כסף kessef or the other way around? Doesn't matter who
initiates. Right, now I'm thinking about the person who wants the change,
you know, I have two I want more loose change, I want
to give you whatever it is. Meaning if it worked the same
way, like, you know, A object and subject, just happens to be
this way. Yeah, that's why it says, if that's if you that's
because you wanted to get the כסף kessef or זהב zahav or
whatever it was. No. No. It says no, it makes no What
do you mean want? There's two sides of a transaction. One side
wants one thing, the other wants the other. It makes no difference
who's the initiator is, which is why the משנה Mishnah says it
in both ways. Okay? It doesn't matter whether you're coming and wanting
to get silver, you're coming and wanting to get gold. You have
gold and silver being exchanged, the gold is the object, the silver
the silver is the money. So no matter which way it goes.
Yeah, what do you mean what you want? There's the other side
of the transaction. Doesn't matter who initiates it. I thought it was
sort of like, you know, you go to a money exchange or...
No, has nothing to do with who initiates or with anything. I
don't care, we're blind to that. Money gold is being exchanged for
silver. Vis-a-vis silver, gold is the object. Silver is the more widely
accepted currency. The way about thinking about it is, you know, thousand
dollar bills and hundred dollar bills, okay? Thousand dollar bills, you want
a thousand dollar bill, you go into some, you know, special place
to buy it or whatever. That's not currency. Hundred dollar bills are
currency. I don't know about hundreds versus twenties, maybe it depends what
type of circles you circulate in. Okay? So it has no nothing
to do with who the people are and who initiates it. All
right, so מעות רעות קונות את היפות, maot raot konot et hayafot,
so bad money is the object and good money is the money,
והיפות אינן קונות את הרעות, vehayafot einan konot et haraot, but if
you take possession of the good money, then the other bad money
has not the sale is not final. אסימון, asimon, which is a
coin that has no... that has not been minted, okay, so it's
the perfect—it's exactly the right thing, it's got the—what's it called? The
blank. Okay, and remember, all this has precious metal content. So its
value probably is the same in precious metal as after the minting.
But once it's been minted, the minting—what minting would do is it
would tell people, you can trust that this is pure silver of
the said weight, right? That's what the act of minting would do.
So you have this unminted coin. So that, אסימון קונה את המטבע,
asimon koneh es hamatbeah, so that is an object vis-a-vis minted coins.
And you'll use the word מטבע matbeah from the word, from מטבע
matbeah means to have been minted. והמטבע אינו קונה אסימון, vehamatbeah eino
koneh asimon, but obviously the reverse is not true. The minted coin
is if you take possession of it, the sale is not final.
Because it is considered money vis-a-vis the אסימון asimon which is the
object. המטבע אינו קונה... hamatbeah eino koneh... Okay, so now, מטלטלין קונין
את המטבע. metaltelin konin es hamatbeah. So now we get to what
should have been the first point, right? That's the paradigm statement. Okay,
chattel, things that we all recognize are objects and not money. When
you take possession of them, the money is owed. המטבע אינו קונה
מטלטלין, hamatbeah eino koneh metaltelin, but the reverse is not true. If
you take possession of the money, the other side does not the
sale is not final. And the other side does not own that
now, the chattel. כל המטלטלין קונין זה את זה. kol hametaltelin konin
zeh es zeh. Now, not only that, but let's say you have
two things. For we won't allow both things to be considered money.
Because since the principle is the sale was final when you take
possession of the object, not of the money, you can't call both
things money. Then the sale will never be final. You have to
identify one of them as the object. But we can have both
of the things being objects, if you're doing not barter, you're not
doing a sale, you're doing a barter. I'm going to swap you
my cow for your donkey. Okay, so which one do you have
to take possession of for the sale to be final? And the
answer is either one. If they're both objects, then you take possession
of either. כל המטלטלין kol hametaltelin what? המטבע אינו קונה מטלטלין, hamatbeah
eino koneh metaltelin, explain that. Yeah, that's the classic point. מטבע—מטלטלין קונין
את המטבע. konin es hamatbeah. That's two different... המטלטלין קונין המטבע. hametaltelin
konin hamatbeah. That's the classic thing. I am selling you my iPhone
here for $300. Okay? So this is my מטלטלין. metaltelin. Your $300
is your מטבע. matbeah So it's המטבע אינו קונה מטלטלין. hamatbeah eino
koneh metaltelin. If I take possession of your $300, you don't yet
own my iPhone. The sale is not final. Okay? But מטלטלין metaltelin
are קונין את המטבע. konin es hamatbeah. When you take possession of
my iPhone, then I own I own your $300. You owe me
the $300. As if those $300 got burned. No, so that's right.
So thank you for pointing that out. The language here is confusing,
because it's not really true that now the money in your pocket
I own. I mean, you can decide what $300 to give me.
You might not even have the cash on you. You might wait
a month to pay me up. So it's not like I owe
a concrete $300 of yours and now you're a שומר shomer on
it. No, that's the point, those $300 get the transaction is effective,
so you still have to give me the $300. Right, right, but
correct, but it's not literally קונין את המטבע. I don't own your
money. You owe me the money. Okay. כל המטלטלין קונין זה את
זה. kol hametaltelin konin zeh es zeh. If you have a barter,
then any one object finalizes the transaction and the other object is
owned.
And here actually we are talking about owning the concrete object.
Okay, I take possession of your cow, you own my donkey. כיצד?
keitzad? משך הימנו פירות.
mashach himenu peiros.
Now, of course the כיצד keitzad here is
not going on מטלטלין זה את
זה.
metaltelin zeh
es zeh.
It's going on מטלטלין metaltelin and מטבע. matbeah. Okay? So this is
and this is like the paradigm, this
is what we should have started with.
That there's money and an object. משך הימנו פירות ולא נתן לו
מעות. mashach himenu peiros velo nasan lo maos. If you draw the
fruit you do משיכה meshicha on the fruit, you draw the fruit
into you, so you did an act of possession of the fruit,
but you did not pay the guy for the money, אינו יכול
לחזור בו. eino yachol lachzor bo. You cannot now retract. The sale
is final. נתן לו מעות ולא משך הימנו פירות.
nasan lo
maos velo mashach himenu peiros.
If you gave the storekeeper the money and you have yet to
take possession of the fruit, יכול לחזור בו. yachol lachzor bo. Then
the sale is not final. You can retract. אבל אמרו, aval amru,
but they said, מי שפרע מאנשי דור המבול ומדור הפלגה, mi shepara
me'anshei dor hamabul umidor hapalaga, the one who here very appropriate for
this week's פרשה, parsha, or last week's פרשה, parsha, the one who
who took back punishment, recompense, as it were, from the people of
the flood and the people of the dispersion, of the tower of
Babel, הוא עתיד
ליפרע ממי שאינו עומד בדיבורו,
hu
asid
lipara mimi she'eino omed bediburo, he will eventually take punishment, recompense from
the person who does not stand by his word.
Which is interesting.
Like, why is it דור הפלגה dor hapalaga and דור? dor? Yeah,
why? Why? Did they not were they not did they not keep
their word? Yeah, so what? חמס. chamas. They took stuff that wasn't
theirs.
That was not דור הפלגה.
dor hapalaga. Through through yes, that was דור המבול. dor hamabul.
They were committing in terms of business transactions through I know, but
it's still funny why that's the— example. Maybe, I don't know, we'll
see in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, we'll also see whether, to what
degree also, does this mean that like when you do this you
get a rabbinic curse, you know, this is often, you know, understood
as it's going to be understood in גמרא Gemara as a type
of a curse that you get. Anyway, right, so we'll see about
that. Okay. So, רבי, Rabbi, if you signed a contract for it,
does that make a difference? In other words, like you sign a
contract, I'm going to, when, you know, with, you know what I'm
saying, like, and there's money, like, you know, does that, does that
hold? So, well, yeah, I mean there's a question about how, about
what creates a binding contract in הלכה Halacha because it's not so
obvious that you can, you know, there's a problem about אומר אתן,
omer eten, you can't like obligate yourself to do something. You know,
so mostly הלכה Halacha knows about doing transactions that affect immediate reality.
I now owe you money, I'm now hired to you, that you
can have employment, you now own something, but a contract that sort
of requires performance later and has consequences for lack of performance or
whatever, that's a whole question about how הלכה Halacha can even, you
know, does הלכה Halacha even recognize that? So that's a different issue.
Okay. רבי שמעון אומר כל הכסף בידו ידו על העליונה. Rabbi Shimon
omer kol hakesef beyado yado al ha'elyona. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
that actually, you know, the ability to reverse a transaction when one
person took the money is not two-sided. It's the transaction, the person
who's holding on to the money can decide if the money's been
paid and the object hasn't been taken, a minute ago we said
that, you know, it could be reversed, which means either side could
reverse it. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says only the guy holding the
money can reverse it. He has all the power. He's got the
money in his pocket so he can decide to give the money
back or to, he can decide to give the object. But the
side that has given the money, he's basically given up his power
and his control of the situation and he can't, so the basic
point is don't give the money till you get the object. I
mean, this obviously thing would mean that you're really stupid to be
giving the money, right? The other says okay, I'll give you the
money now, worst case scenario I can always go back and I
can always retract. Okay, according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it's totally
giving the power to the other side. What? If it's a defective
object don't you have a right? Yeah, that's מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut.
But we're not talking about מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. Okay, let's take
a look. Okay, so the principle is clear, right, that a, the
קנין kinyan is sale, the, the transaction is final when you take
what's defined as the object. That there can be two objects but
there can't be two moneys in any transaction. And if the sale
isn't final but the money changed hands, then that creates a middle-level
state where you, it's not fully binding, you can back out, but
there is some consequence, this מי שפרע mi shepara consequence. And according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon actually the right to back out is
only on one side. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to focus in
on this first point about what is considered money when you're dealing
with different types of money. Okay. מתני לה רבי לרבי שמעון בריה.
Masni lah Rabbi le-Rabbi Shimon breih. So רבי Rabbi taught this משנה
Mishna to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon his son. Wait, this isn't the
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה, Mishna, is it? No, the
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishna is רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon Bar Yochai. הזהב קונה את הכסף, Hazahav koneh es
hakesef, which is the version that we have, which means that silver
is money vis-a-vis gold. אמר ליה, Amar leih, רבי, Rabbi, he said
to him, רבי, Rabbi, and of course he didn't call him my
father, so presumably he was calling him my master. שנית לנו בילדותך,
Shenisa lanu beyalduscha, you taught us when you were young. Okay, couldn't
have been that young, he still was teaching his son. Anyway, you
taught us in your youth הכסף קונה את הזהב. hakesef koneh es
hazahav. Okay, that actually silver is the object and gold is the
money. ותשנה לנו בזקנותך, Vesishneh lanu beziknuscha, now you're going to teach
us in your old age הזהב קונה את הכסף, hazahav koneh es
hakesef, the reverse? That gold is the object and silver is the
money? So now the גמרא Gemara interjects because we don't know what
רבי Rabbi answered, so the גמרא's Gemara going to interject. בילדותיה מאי
סבר ובזקנותיה מאי סבר. Beyaldusei mai savar u-veziknusei mai savar. What was
his position in his youth and what was his position in his
older age? בילדותיה סבר, Beyaldusei savar, in his youth where he said
that gold is always the money and silver is the object, he
said דהבא דחשיב הוי טבעא. dahava de-chashiv havei tiva. Gold is the
most important, the gold standard. Okay? So everything else is relative to
gold. Gold is the מטבע. matbeah. כספא דלא חשיב הוי פירא, Kaspa
d'lo chashiv havei peira, money that's silver that's not as important, right,
it's not as rare and it's not as valued in society and
so on, then הוי פירא, havei peira, that's considered the object, the
fruit. וקני ליה פירא לטבעא. Vekani lei peira letiva. And therefore the
fruit is buys, the fruit is the object vis-a-vis the gold which
is the money. Now here, by the way, רש"י Rashi points out
and the גמרא's Gemara going to point out soon, here's another way
of thinking about it beyond just an arbitrary assigning of labels which
determines, you know, in this type of a transaction. Let's say that,
you know, when we were on the gold standard, right, wasn't there
a fixed ratio of gold to silver? Was it 32 to 1
or something like that? Do people remember that? That's probably before you
were, that's not before your time, I remember that there was some
fixed 32 to 1 ratio in my time anyway between like silver
to gold. Okay, but if you really allow for a free market,
right, you know, then and you have gold coins and silver coins,
then at certain times, you know, 25 silver, there'll be 25 silver
coins for every one gold. Sometimes it'll be 20 and sometimes it'll
be 30, right? It depends on the relative value of the two.
So let's... Let's say let's say last year it was 25 silver
to one gold and this year it's 20 silver to one gold.
How do you articulate that? One way of saying it is is
that the price of silver went up, right? The other way of
saying it is the price of gold went down, okay? So which
way do you think of it? So that reflects what basically is
your base currency, right? If your base currency is silver, so you
define everything in terms of silver. So in that case you would
say the price of gold went down.
I can get gold cheaper now, price of gold went down. But
if gold is your basic currency, you say the price of silver
went up. It costs me more money now to buy silver. Okay,
so that is the question. When you have these currencies of different
precious metals and which have different relative values at different times to
one another, which do you define as the currency and which do
you define everything else's price fluctuates in relative, you know, vis-à-vis what
you've defined as your base currency? Okay, so that's the
question. Okay, so when he was younger, he said that gold, gold
is the most important thing, so gold is the standard. That's the
money and everything else changes its price vis-à-vis gold. בזיקנותו סבר, Biziknusei
savar, in his old age he said, כספא דחריף הוי טיבעא, Kaspah
d'charif havei tiva, no, no, no, gold might be more valuable, but
you know, but silver is much more in wide use, right? Because
very few people can afford gold and have gold coins, okay? So
the currency that everybody uses is silver. So therefore, you know, silver
is how you define what prices are. And when the price the
amount of silver to gold changes, it's the price of gold that
is fluctuating because silver is the standard of currency. Know more about
money he got older... well, or he had well, right,
maybe, different perspective on things.
דהבא דלא חריף, Dahava d'lo charif, gold which is not as widespread,
הוי פירא וקרי ליה פירא. havei peira veka'rei leh peira. Okay, so
in our משנה Mishna where he says הזהב קונה את הכסף, Hazahav
koneh es hakesef, he says it doesn't matter that gold is more
valuable, silver which is more widespread, which is the type of currency
that everybody references things in, that is the currency and gold is
the object. Now, by the way, two important things to note. One
is in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi's גירסא girsa of the
משנה Mishna is רבי בילדותו, Rebbi be'Yalduso, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi's גירסא girsa
of the משנה Mishna is הכסף קונה את הזהב הזהב אינו קונה
את הכסף. Hakesef koneh es hazahav hazahav eino koneh es hakesef. So
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi's name of this פרק perek is not הזהב, Hazahav,
ירושלמי Yerushalmi's name of this פרק perek is הכסף. Hakesef. Okay, so
it's like I think it's like the only time in ש"ס Shas
you actually have a different name of a פרק perek because actually
it has the different first word of the משנה. Mishna. The other
point to note is that, and I didn't get a chance to
check this up, but is that there is that there's something about
sort of like Roman history. I wanted Charlie to be here because
I figured I wouldn't have to look it up, Charlie could tell
us. But anyway, about about having to do with gold and silver
and the availabilities of the currencies and so on that is sort
of relevant, you know, to this, because because of רבי Rebbi was
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right? But within the Roman Empire, I
think the availability of gold and silver and like which was the
standard coinage or whatever, from what I vaguely remember, I read about
it a while ago. I don't know if anybody has שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz
and can check if he discusses it. But anyway, there was some
relevant historical background to this. Gold was the standard, okay, that's true.
Okay, let's keep on going. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, said
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, okay, said רב אשי, Rav Ashi, כי ילדותו
מסתברא, Ki Yalduso mistabra, it actually makes sense like his youth, that
gold, gold is the most important thing, so gold is the standard,
that's the currency. דקתני, De'katani, because it says, הנחושת קונה את הכסף,
Hanechoshes koneh es hakesef, because it says that copper coins are the
object vis-à-vis silver which is the currency. So if you ask what's
more widespread, right, if your whole standard was sort of like widespread,
you would say well most people can't afford silver either, most people
use copper coins, okay? Most people, you know, so therefore how many
people trade in hundred dollar bills? Most people, their standards are twenties.
Some people even, depends, sometimes it's like an interesting commentary based on
the neighborhood you're in whether the ATM gives out twenties or tens,
right? Anyway, so most people use the copper coins. So if he
actually is holding that you go by the widespread usage, then copper
should be the money vis-à-vis silver, okay? So therefore it actually makes
sense that the original משנה, Mishna, right, was on the hierarchy of
currency, that the original משנה Mishna was זהב כסף נחושת, Zahav kesef
nechoshes, because that would be by value and that would mean therefore
that זהב zahav is the currency vis-à-vis כסף kesef and כסף kesef
is the currency vis-à-vis נחושת. nechoshes. No, I got it right.
זהב, Zahav, נחושת, nechoshes,
oh I'm sorry, I thought you meant... reverse the order. Okay, anyway.
Okay, so that, so what he's saying is it makes sense that
this is the proper hierarchy. So if that's the proper hierarchy, the
גרסא geirsa should be כסף קונה את הזהב. Kesef koneh et hazahav.
All right? Why? Because according to our משנה, mishna, right, the hierarchy
is the following: כסף, זהב, נחושת. Kesef, zahav, nechoshet. Okay, because this
we said is the most widespread, and therefore that's money vis-a-vis this.
Okay? Right? That's true, that's clear, yeah, okay. But the problem therefore
is, if you're going by widespread, why is this money vis-a-vis נחושת?
nechoshet? נחושת nechoshet is more widespread than כסף. kesef. So נחושת nechoshet
should be on the top. So the- reading the משנה mishna the
way we have it, he says doesn't make sense. But maybe he
just did it also the way the Torah says: זהב וכסף ונחושת.
Zahav, v'kesef, u'nechoshet. No, I don't know. No, no. It's not a
question of order. It's a question of the פסק. psak. Did Steinsaltz
say anything, Jenna?
No? All right, I'll have to look it up.
Okay,
so
I'll have to give Charlie a call. So he says like this.
אמר רב אשי כי ילדותיה מסתברא. Amar Rav Ashi, ki yeldusa mistabra.
Actually, the original text of the משנה, mishna, because to some degree,
if רבי Rebbe is writing the משנה, mishna, you can't prove something
from the way he wrote the משנה. mishna. But as רש"י Rashi
says, he's not writing the משנה, mishna, he's editing the משנה. mishna.
So the question is, which is the right text of the original
משנה mishna that רבי Rebbe received? And we are saying that the
right text should be that כסף kesef is the- that gold is
the standard. Why? מדקתני הנחושת קונה את הכסף. Mi-dekatni hanechoshet koneh et
hakesef. Because the end of the משנה mishna is not in dispute.
The end of the משנה mishna says, copper is the object vis-a-vis
silver. Silver is the currency- silver is the currency. So אי אמרת
בשלמא דכספא לגבי דהבא פירא, iy amart bishlama d'kaspa legabei dahva peira,
if you say that silver
vis-a-vis gold, silver is the object and gold is the currency, so
it's very clear. The more valuable something is, the more it's considered
currency vis-a-vis something that is of a lesser metal. Okay, so היינו
דקתני הנחושת קונה את הכסף. havei hainu de-katni hanechoshet koneh et hakesef.
That's why we say that נחושת nechoshet is the object and silver
is the money. דאף על גב דלגבי דהבא פירא הוי, De-af al
gav de-gabai dahva peira havi, although silver is considered fruit vis-a-vis- vis-a-vis
gold, gold is the highest currency, but לגבי נחושת legabei nechoshet vis-a-vis
something that's of a lesser, you know, a lesser metal, טיבעא הוי,
tiva havay, it- it is currency, right? That's the whole point in
the משנה, mishna, right? That things can be relative to a different
coinage. There's not like one- it's not silver's always an object. In
most cases, silver's money. Vis-a-vis gold, it's an object. Vis-a-vis copper, it's-
it's currency. So that's clear, right? The hierarchy is clear. It goes
by the value of the metal. The higher value of the metal
is the currency vis-a-vis something of a lower value. So gold and
silver, gold is the- gold is the currency, silver is the object.
Silver and- and copper, copper- silver's the currency, copper is the object.
So
the reading of the משנה mishna כסף קונה את הזהב, kesef koneh
et hazahav, that would be the reading that makes sense. אלא אי
אמרת כספא לגבי דהבא טיבעא הוי, Ella iy amart kaspa legabei dahva
tiva havay, but if you say the way to determine what is
the currency is not by the value of the metal, but by
the widespread nature of it, so if silver is considered to be
currency vis-a-vis gold, השתא לגבי דהבא דחשיב מיניה אמרת טיבעא הוי, hashta
legabei dahva de-chashiv minei amart tiva havay,
you're going to tell me that when- that vis-a-vis
gold, which is more weighty than it, you know, silver is going
to be considered to be the
currency. לגבי
נחושת דאיהו חשיב ואיהו חריף מיבעיא? legabei nechoshet de-ihu chashiv v'ihu charif
mi-ba-yei? So it would be- why would you have to tell me
that vis-a-vis- so I confused you because I raised the wrong question,
which is- which we'll get to. I always do that, I jump
ahead too- I'm thinking too much to the end of the discussion.
Anyway, גמרא gemara says it's like- it's obvious that sil- if silver
vis-a-vis gold is considered to be the currency, because even though it's
not as valuable as gold, it's more widespread, so it's obvious that
vis-a-vis, you know, copper, it would be considered the currency, because it's-
it's more valuable than copper, so there's two reasons to make it
the currency. It's not logical because the response is: copper's actually more
widespread than silver, which is what- yes.
Sorry, just I have an email from Charlie that says: silver was
the standard metal for coins in the Roman Empire, but in the
Middle Ages, gold coins had disappeared from Europe.
Okay, so silver was the standard in the Roman Empire, which would
explain זקנותו, ziknuso, but it wouldn't explain ילדותו, yelduso, because that's what
the end- the- you know, with זקנותו ziknuso he's saying that- was
he listening live? Okay, anyway, yes.
I sort of understand it like- the- what I proposed earlier. I
think- obviously not, but like, you know, I think a reasonable case
anyway could be made for, depends on your understanding of the transaction.
I'm saying I want to buy gold from you. I heard that
Michael, but that's not the פסק psak of the משנה. mishna. Let's
keep on going. Okay, okay, so איצטריך. it-stareich. So anyway, the גמרא
gemara is saying that it's not that the משנה mishna would be
wrong, but it would be obvious that if silver's considered currency vis-a-vis
gold, it should certainly be currency vis-a-vis something of lesser value, something
like copper. So the גמרא gemara says no, איצטריך, it-stareich, the משנה
mishna would have had to tell me that. סלקא דעתך אמינא הני
פריטי באתרא דסגי אינהו חריפי טפי. Salka daitach amina hani priti be-atra
de-sagi inu charifi tfei. I had jumped ahead. I might have thought
that even the פרוטות, prutot, the פרוטות prutos copper, the copper coins
in the place where they are, where they are used, they're actually
used much more in a widespread way than silver. Okay? So silver
may be, silver you can go to any place, try to go
to a store and buy something with a thousand
pennies, right? Certain money you can use anywhere and everybody accepts it,
but in certain
locales, in poor
countryside, copper is what everybody uses, not silver. So therefore, I would
have said הוי אמינא havah amina הני פרוטי hani pruti these copper
coins באתרא דסגי ba'atra d'sagi in the place where they are sort
of transacted, אינהו חריפי טפי inhu kharifei tfei they're more widespread מכספא
mikhaspa than silver, so אימא טיבעא הוי, eima tiva havei, so actually
that's a reasonable point. If you go by what is more in
use, and that's why silver's the currency vis-a-vis gold, so maybe in
certain locales copper should be the currency vis-a-vis silver. קא משמע לן
Kamashma lan we don't say that. כיון דאיכא דוכתא דלא סגי ביה
Keivan d'ika dukhta d'lo sagi bei since there are places that don't
accept copper coins, okay, פירא הוי. peira havei. Everything is framed in
the—it is true, in some places, people will be so poor or
whatever, but whatever, nobody will ever use a silver coin, right? Everybody
will always transact. But a silver coin is—but silver's always accepted, and
silver defines the price, the standard of prices are defined in terms
of silver even if in a certain place you're going to use
copper coins. So anyway, that's what it says. So we have one
way of understanding it, which is Rabbi in his youth, which is
the gold is the standard, and the more valuable the metal, it's
the currency vis-a-vis the thing of lesser value. And we have this
other way, which is more complicated. No, no, no, the currency is
not always based on the value of the metal. It could be
based on how widespread its usage is, whether it's the standard type
of a currency. Okay, but that's—but widespread usage is not the only
definition. Even if in some places copper is more widespread than silver,
silver's always going to be the standard. And that gets consistent with
what Charlie said, that silver in the Roman Empire was the standard.
Okay, so it's defined in terms of the silver standard. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. קא משמע לן כיון
דאיכא דוכתא דלא סגי ביה פירא הוי. Kamashma lan keivan d'ika dukhta
d'lo sagi bei peira havei. ואף רבי חייא סבר דהבא טיבעא הוי.
V'af Rabi Khiya savar daha'va tiva havei. And even רבי חייא Rabi
Khiya held like Rabbi in his youth, okay, that gold was the
standard. So the gold standard or the silver standard? Now some people
are saying that we have to, I just read, the stocks market
plunged, people are buying gold. Okay, anyway, מעניינא דיומא. me'inyana deyoma. Anyway,
טיבעא הוי. tiva havei. דורב אוזיף דינרי מברתיה דרבי חייא. De'Rav ozif
dinarei m'bartei d'Rabi Khiya. Rav borrowed money from רבי חייא's Rabi Khiya
daughter. So look at this, that's already fascinating. רבי חייא's Rabi Khiya
daughter was a businesswoman. לסוף יקרו דינרי. L'sof ikru dinarei. In the
end, okay, the דינרי dinarei which were the gold—which are gold דינרי,
dinarei, okay, they—their value went up. Meaning, originally he borrowed ten gold
coins. Ten gold coins at that time would have gone for 250
silver. But now when it's time to pay back, okay, ten gold
coins is going for 300 silver. How much does he owe? He
didn't want to give her רבית. ribit. So he's by giving her
back ten coins, ten gold coins, you're giving her back—maybe that's רבית,
ribit, you're giving her back something that's worth more silver coins than
what you borrowed. All right? But if gold is the standard, if
gold defines the currency, then that just means that the price of
silver has gone down. Gold is always seen to be the same,
everything else changes its price, its value vis-a-vis it. So this is
a very relevant part of this question of what's the currency, right?
Is he allowed to rule in a case that
might—he might not be—I don't know, we're actually going to see, I
don't know, because it wasn't like he was—it wasn't like a טועה
בדבר משנה. to'eh b'dvar mishnah. Like he was prepared to give her
back the ten coins. He just wanted to make sure it wasn't
רבית. ribit. Yeah.
And before we get into that, just some going back to the
משנה. Mishnah. How were we reading it now as זהב קונה את
הכסף? zahav koneh et hakesef?
No, it's clear that our משנה Mishnah that the בבלי Bavli sort
of has is זהב קונה. zahav koneh. But the question is do
we פסקן pasken that? Because now we're quoting a lot of תנאים
Tannaim or whatever that actually prefer the earlier rulings.
So
the conclusion from this part at least is that we will go
by כסף קונה, kesef koneh, at least that—Right. The discussion here is
maybe reject Rabbi's older פסק psak and go by his younger פסק.
psak. And רבי חייא Rabi Khiya would agree with that. רבי חייא
Rabi Khiya seems to be—so let's take a look. לסוף יקרו דינרי.
L'sof ikru dinarei. In the end, the gold coins went up in
value, or the other way of saying it is everything else went
down in value. אתא לקמיה דרבי חייא. Ata l'kamei d'Rabi Khiya. He
came to רבי חייא. Rabi Khiya. אמר ליה זיל שלים לה טבין
ותקילין. Amar lei zil shlim la tavin v'takilin. Go pay her good
and full weight coins. Okay, yes, pay her back the full ten
gold coins that you borrowed even though now they're worth 300 silver
coins. So אי אמרת ei amart בשלמא דהבא טיבעא הוי bishlama daha'va
tiva havei gold is the currency, שפיר, shapir, it's good. What really
happened is the price of silver went down. Gold is—always remains the
same.
אלא אי אמרת פירא
הוי
ela ei
amart peira
havei
but if— If it is the object, so סאה בסאה ואסור. sea
b'sea v'assur. So first so then what you're doing
is, the first thing you're doing is you borrowed something worth 250
gold coins and you gave her back something worth, I mean 250
silver, and you gave her back something worth 300 silver. So you
gave her back something of greater value than you borrowed, so that's
a type of a ריבית. ribbis. Now actually the principle of סאה
בסאה, sea b'sea, and this is important, I mean it's going to
be mostly next פרק perek what's important to introduce now, is a
problem even if the value doesn't change because the value might change.
When I go ahead and I borrow, if I say, you know
you're not going to say "Could I borrow two eggs?" and you
give me two eggs. Okay, I'm not allowed to say that because
then when I give you back two eggs, "Could I borrow two
eggs?" Okay. "Can you lend me?" I say, "Can
you borrow? Can you lend me two eggs?" Why can you not
say that? Because even if when I pay you back the next
day the price of eggs hasn't changed, but it might change. And
therefore, borrowing an object and paying back an object is opening the
door for the fact that you're going to give something back of
greater value than what you took. Even though you're giving me back
two eggs too, the next day. Exactly, because the question of ריבית
ribbis is because everything is defined in, isn't that what they say
right? What is it? You know, a cynic, somebody who knows the
cost of everything and the value of nothing. So ריבית, ribbis, everything
is defined in terms of its dollar value. Okay? You don't borrow
eggs. You borrow the what you borrowed was the how much money
did you borrow? What was the value? What was the price of
what you borrowed? Basically, "Can I have two eggs?" So yeah, you
should say, "Can I have two eggs?" Okay, so you're supposed to
say "Can I have two eggs?" And then after say, "Here, I
wanted to give you two eggs because you were so nice to
give me two eggs yesterday." Okay. It's hard to get into the
habit of saying that with your next-door neighbor. If you're friendly enough,
you just say, "Hey, do you have any eggs? Oh, can I
come over? Can, you know, whatever?" and you don't actually say the
word borrow. But if you say the word borrow, what you've done
is you've borrowed something worth a certain dollar value. And then when
you give it back, you might be giving back something worth a
greater dollar value. Okay? So that actually is considered a concern, it's
a rabbinic concern of ריבית. ribbis. You're not supposed to do it
even if the prices don't fluctuate because they might. So in this
case, the price is definitely fluctuating. So the point is, how would
we allow it? Yes, you're giving back 10 gold coins, but if
we define things in terms of silver, you're giving back something of
greater value than you received. So it would be a ריבית ribbis
concern. So it must be that the currency, the definition of the
value of something, is the gold value, not the silver value. Okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says, "הוי ליה סאה בסאה ואסור." havei lei
sea b'sea v'assur. It would have been forbidden because it would have
been like, you know, a gallon for a gallon, it would have
been trading objects which you're not allowed to do. So it must
be that this was all this was considered the currency and therefore
it was acceptable. Now by the way, I'll just say something because
it's not complicated enough, which is that the גמרא Gemara later is
going to question the idea of maybe we can allow for multiple
things being defined as currency and we only have to choose when
they're both coming in, when
they're being dealt with together. Meaning it could be that if I
borrowed gold coins from you, I'm entitled to give you back gold
regardless of the price of silver. And if I borrowed silver from
Michael, I'm entitled to give him back silver regardless of the price
of gold, because each one by itself is currency. The only question
is when you're swapping gold for silver, you gotta pick. Okay, so
that's a possibility. But anyway, but the גמרא Gemara now is assuming
it's like one or the other. So the גמרא Gemara is saying
there's got to be one standard and if you borrow gold and
give back gold, that proves that it's the gold standard, that we're
not concerned with its different value vis-a-vis silver. All right.
Why would the eggs change then? If it's an egg for an
egg, if it's gold for gold...
because an egg is never money. Oh, that's right. Okay. Yeah, but
gold, we're saying gold is the currency standard, so gold always has
the same value. You know what the value of 10 gold coins
is? 10 gold coins. Okay? The gold, the value of the currency
is always the same. It's everything else that fluctuates. All right. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. רב דינרי הוה ליה. Rav dinarei hava lei. וכיון דהוו ליה
דינרי, v'kivan d'havu lei dinarei, no no no, so the גמרא Gemara
says wait, I have a way out of it. We could say
that gold coins is, that the standard is silver and nevertheless he
was allowed to borrow gold and pay back gold, the same amount.
Why? Because he actually had gold coins in his possession. Back in
his house, he had 10 gold coins. Okay, but he couldn't run
back there, they didn't have ATM machines, and רבי חייא's Rebbi Chiya
daughter was with him. He said, "Quick, lend me 10 gold coins,
I have a great business opportunity." But he had the money back
in his house. So since he had the money back in his
house, so דכי הוו ליה דינרי, de'ki havu lei dinarei, נאמר לו,
ne'emar lo, it's like
if you say "הב לי עד שיבוא בני או עד שאמצא מפתח."
hav li ad she'yavo beni o ad she'emtza mafte'ach. "Lend me this
until my son comes home or until I can find the key
to my house." Meaning that's a case where סאה בסאה sea b'sea
is okay, because there what we conceptualize it is, if I go
you know over to Eli and I say, "Eli, lend me 10
gold coins," or let me say "Two eggs." "Lend me two eggs.
I'm here and I'm baking bread, I need the two eggs for
my recipe," okay, but we're here at, I don't know, we're here
at some show bakeathon and I don't want to run back to
my house and get the two eggs.
Your house
is near, right?
Like, let's say.
No, it doesn't matter. It doesn't matter. So yes, so it, it
removes the problem of paying back at a later time because we
conceptualize it like you did an immediate swap right now. So if
I say lend me 10 gold coins, I can't, I need to
feed this business deal, I can't go back to my house, but
I have it in my house. You give me 10 gold coins,
it's like right away I swap them with you for the 10
gold coins in my house and that's allowed. So maybe this was
a special case and maybe gold is not the standard, maybe gold
really is considered the פרי *peri* and silver is the טבע *tiba*.
And you can't say lend me because I plan on going to
the supermarket later today.
Exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay.
Unless the 10 gold coins in your house were stolen.
Well, right. So it's only, it's only, that's true. So it's not
really, it's not really that the other person owns it. It's as
if the other person owns it, because the whole idea that סאה
בסאה *se'ah b'se'ah* is a ריבית *ribbis* problem is a rabbinic issue,
so we allow this type of a fiction to solve it. But
you're right. It's not really like the person owes, owns the money
in my house just yet. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. Okay, נפשוט *nifshot*. Okay, so we haven't proven it,
but from the רב חייא *Rav Chiya* case it sounds like gold
is the standard and not silver. Okay, אמר רבא *amar Rava*, האי
תנא סבר דהבא טיבעא tib'a, הוי *hai tanna savar de-hava tiva hovei*
and the following תנא *tanna* also holds that gold is the standard
and not silver. How do we know? דתניא *de-tanya*, תניא ברייתא *tanya
baraita*. פרוטה perutah שאמרו *prutah she-ameru*, when they said a פרוטה perutah
*prutah*, this is a משנה Mishnah, עדיות *Mishnah Eduyot* which is and
saying when the rabbis speak about a פרוטה perutah *prutah*, like they
do by קידושין *kiddushin*, right? קידושין *kiddushin* is with a שווה פרוטה
perutah *shaveh prutah*. אחד משמונה באיסר האיטלקי *echad mi-shmoneh be-issar ha-italki*, it's
one-eighth of an Italian איסר issar *issar*. למאי נפקא מינה *lemai nafka
mina*, and what is the relevance of knowing what the, how much
a פרוטה perutah *prutah* is worth? לקידושי אשה *le-kiddushei isha*, for קידושין
*kiddushin*, right? A פרוטה perutah *prutah* makes the whole difference. Okay, איסר
issar, *issar*, now how much is an Italian איסר *issar*?
That's אחד מעשרים וארבע בדינר של כסף *echad mi-esrim v'arba b'dinar shel
kesef*, it's 1/24th of a silver דינר dinar. *dinar*, which is times
eight is what, 160, 32, 192 פרוטות perutot *prutos* per
silver דינר dinar? *dinar*. Okay? So 1/24th of a silver דינר dinar.
*dinar*. למאי נפקא מינה, למקח וממכר *lemai nafka mina, le-mekach u-mimkar*. Why
is that relevant? For purchase. What does that mean purchase? So רש"י
*Rashi* says that if you basically sell, your purchase here for רש"י
*Rashi* doesn't mean purchase, it basically means money changing. If you're basically
buying a silver דינר dinar, *dinar* for more, for like less than
24, whatever these, איסרין *issars* are, then,
then, then you might be cheating the seller. And if you're buying
it for more than 24 איסרין *issars*, he might be cheating you.
So it's important to know the rate of exchange so people aren't
cheated when they swap money. That's sort of what, that's what רש"י
*Rashi* explains.
It's sort of the thing they're always like 100 pennies to a
dollar.
Yeah, basically. Although yes, but תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says it means something
else. I'll get to תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* in a minute. Let's keep
on reading though. Okay, דינר dinar של כסף אחד מעשרים וחמישה בדינר
של זהב *dinar shel kesef echad me-esrim v'chamisha b'dinar shel zahav*. A
silver דינר dinar, *dinar* is 1/25th of a gold דינר dinar, *dinar*.
למאי נפקא מינה, לפדיון הבן *lemai nafka mina, le-pidyon haben*. For פדיון
הבן pidyon haben *pidyon haben*, because a פדיון הבן pidyon haben *pidyon
haben* is basically based on, it's worth, a פדיון הבן pidyon haben
*pidyon haben* is 20 silver דינרי *dinarei*. It's five שקל *shekel*, a
שקל *shekel* is four דינר dinar *dinar*, so פדיון הבן pidyon haben
*pidyon haben* is 20 silver דינרי *dinarei*. Okay, so a gold דינר
*dinar* here, a gold דינר *dinar* is 25 silver. פדיון הבן pidyon
haben: *pidyon haben*, although for פדייה *pidya*, it's five שקל *shekel* and
a שקל *shekel* is four silver דינר *dinar*, so it's 20 silver
דינר *dinar*. Okay, that's פדיון הבן pidyon haben. *pidyon haben*. So if
you have a gold coin and you want to use for פדיון
הבן pidyon haben *pidyon haben*, you know that 4/5ths of it, right,
is needed for פדיון הבן *pidyon haben* and 1/5th you get in
return. So if you give the כהן kohen *Kohen* a gold דינר
*dinar*, he has to give you back a fifth of the value
of the gold coin, which under the normal exchange rate would be
five silver coins. Okay, now why does any of this, what does,
how does any of this prove that gold is the standard? So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
So, okay, אי אמרת בשלמא טיבעא הוי *ee amart bishlama tiva hovei*,
if you say gold is the standard, is the currency, so משער
תנא במידי דקאי *meshayyer tanna be-midi de-kayyei*? So how could the... אי
אמרת בשלמא טיבעא הוי *ee amart bishlama tiva hovei*, if it's the
currency, then it makes sense. Then you're defining your פדיון הבן *pidyon
haben* with the fixed amount. One gold coin for פדיון הבן *pidyon
haben* or 4/5ths of a gold coin for פדיון הבן *pidyon haben*.
However much silver and other things fluctuate, the value, you know, this
is the standard and 4/5ths of this is the value of פדיון
הבן *pidyon haben*. Everything else, שקל *shekel*, דינרי *dinarei*, everything else is
relative to this standard. So the standard, so therefore the basic definition
of anything's value is all in terms of gold. Okay? So how
what percentage of a gold coin. So therefore in the end the
פדיון הבן *pidyon haben* we're saying is 4/5ths of the gold coin.
That makes sense in our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. בי שלמא למאן דאמר
טיבעא הוי, אלא אי אמרת פירא הוי, ela ee amart pira havei,
but if gold is פירות, peirot, it's not the fixed standard, so
משחתנא ובידי דאוקי וזול? mashartana ubeidi de'okei vazol? How could you be
saying, you know, the פדיון הבן is is like, you know, four-fifths
of a gold coin? But that's not always going to be the
same value, right? If you define value based in terms of silver
value, that the value of gold is going to fluctuate. And therefore,
זימנין דמהדר ליה כהנא וזימנין דמוסיף להו לכהנא, zimnin demahadar lei kahana
vezimnin demosif la-hu la-kahana,
sometimes the כהן will have to give you back more because the
value of silver has, you know, I'm not getting lost, anyway, has
changed in one of the directions. I can't just think it through.
Anyway, and sometimes he'll give you back less because of the changing
value of silver. So if, if silver were the standard, you cannot
say, oh, the amount of פדיון הבן is four-fifths of a gold
coin, because it really matters how much silver does that gold coin
buy. So clearly if we're saying פדיון הבן in terms of the
gold coin, it means that the gold is considered fixed and everything
else fluctuates vis-a-vis gold. So אלא שמע מינה טיבעא הוי שמע מינה.
Ela shema mina tib'a havei shema mina. You see that gold must
be the standard. That is a good proof and therefore the amount
of פדיון הבן is fixed. Now comes along עולא Ulla and he
says, it's all very nice for the end of the משנה, Mishnah
let's go back to something even more important than פדיון הבן: קידושי
אשה. kiddushei ishah. How about a woman's personal status? That says a
פרוטה perutah vis-a-vis, you know, an איסר and vis-a-vis a silver דינר.
So if you're going to sort of determine, you know, whether the
woman is married based on is it one-twenty-four... one hundred and ninety-sixths
of a silver דינר? But sometimes that might not be a פרוטה
perutah, because that might be less gold than it was than this,
maybe it's a different status vis-a-vis the gold. So, you know, that
should prove that silver's the standard, right? Because you're going to define
the copper פרוטה perutah vis-a-vis a silver דינר. So what...
Yeah, it hits the same common denominator. It's not... it's not טיבעא,
it's the הכרח hechreich of the context.
Yeah,
but the גמרא is still saying if you want to determine that
you need a minimum value of something to do something, you have
to define, right, whether, now you could say it's always one פרוטה
perutah. regardless of what its value is vis-a-vis silver. It's always x
amount of silver, you know, you could sort of say that everything
can equally be a standard unless they're in competition with one another.
But the גמרא is basically understanding that one thing has to define
whether this was a good פדיון הבן. So that's true, but silver
seems to define the percen... you know, the amount of a פרוטה
perutah which would seem to define whether it's a good קידושי אשה.
kiddushei ishah. So that seems to say that silver's a standard. So
how... how does this prove one over the other? So תוספות Tosafot
says that no, no, no. What this means is the reason the
the משנה here keeps on going up, x amount of coins per
איסר, x amount per per silver דינר, x amount of silver דינר
per gold דינר, means that everything lower on the list is defined
in terms of the thing at the end, is defined in terms
of the gold. So the amount of is this פרוטה perutah really
worth a פרוטה perutah is whether
it's whatever percentage it is of the gold coin. And if right
now it actually is less of a percentage of the gold coin,
this פרוטה, then this פרוטה is not worth a פרוטה. This פרוטה
is not good enough for קידושי אשה. kiddushei ishah. So תוספות Tosafot,
actually says the point of the גמרא and the point of this
משנה is not just to say that for פדיון הבן it's based
on the gold coin. It's really to say that everything down the
road, right? So if you've got basically, I mean you could do
the math, if it's one פרוטה equals 196, I think, no, I'm
sorry, 196 פרוטות perutot, is one, you know, silver דינר, and 25
silver is one gold, then one gold is roughly, let's call that
200, is roughly 5,000 פרוטות, okay? So that means that if you
want to know was the קידושי אשה kiddushei ishah good and you
gave her a פרוטה coin, we would not automatically say it's good.
לא! Lo! Let's go ahead and look at the current exchange rate,
right, and the current gold rate, and if it's worth one-five thousandth
of a gold דינר or more, היא מקודשת. hi mekudeshet. And if
it's worth less than that, היא אינה מקודשת. hi einah mekudeshet. Everything
value is always defined... it's a gold standard. It's value defined in
terms of gold. So that's how... that's how תוספות Tosafot, is reading
this. Yes.
It's going to be to that historical moment. In other words, it's...
it was good קידוש kiddush at that moment.
At that moment, that was its value. That is correct. Okay. Now,
by the way...
one minute.
Okay, so now it says like this. If you take a look
by the way at תוספות, Tosafot I just want to pause for
a moment and look at תוספות, אחד מכ"ה בדינר זהב, echad mi-kaf-hei
be-dinar zahav, because it's interesting little historical point. תוספות says, and this
is relevant to what Charlie said, right? What did Charlie say? That
by the Middle Ages silver was no longer the standard, it was
gold...
Gold was no longer the standard at all.
But he said that it was silver. was the standard in the
Roman Empire. Okay, so תוספות *Tosafot*, קשיא לרבינו תם איך היה בימיו
שהיה זהב יקר כל כך שדינר זהב היה שווה כ"ה דינרי של
כסף *Kashya le-Rabbeinu Tam eich haya beyamav shehaya zahav yakar kol kach
shedinar zahav haya shaveh chaf-hei dinei shel kessef*. How could it be
that gold was so valued that one, because presumably the דינרים *dinarim*
are the same weight? So one unit of gold, like one ounce
of gold, was worth 25 ounces of silver. ואתה בזמן הזה *Ve-ata
bazman hazeh*, and nowadays, זקוק זהב שווה לכל היותר י"ב זקוקים של
כסף *Zkuk zahav shaveh le-chol hayoter yod-bet zkukim shel kessef*. At most,
one ounce of gold is worth 12 ounces of silver. So how
could it be that the relative value has fluctuated so much? So
I'm not an economist, I'm sure an economist would say yes, that
does happen. Okay, but whatever, תוספות *Tosafot* רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* couldn't
accept that. How could you go from a 1 to 25 ratio
to 1 to 12 ratio? And תוספות'ס *Tosafot's* answer is it must
be that a gold, what? No, he said the gold דינר *dinar*
was the same size as the silver דינר *dinar*, but gold is
denser. So actually, and he actually suggests also that the gold דינר
*dinar* was thicker. So actually, he says, no, no, no, he wants
to claim that there hasn't been that much fluctuation. One gold ounce
is worth 12 silver ounces, but one gold דינר *dinar*, because it's
more weight than one silver דינר *dinar*. So therefore, it could be
a 1 to 25 in terms of the דינר *dinar* coins. Anyway,
let's get back to the גמרא *Gemara*. It says like this: תנן
התם *Tnan hatam*, we taught over there: בית שמאי אומרים *Beit Shammai
omrim*, לא יעשה אדם סלעים דינרי זהב *Lo ya’aseh adam sla’im dinarei
zahav*. ובית הלל מתירים *U-Veit Hillel matirin*. Okay, so בית שמאי *Beit
Shammai* says that when you are switching your money for מעשר שני
*Ma’aser Sheni*, you have your fruit, you transferred it to gold
דינרי *dinarei*. Now you want to transfer your silver דינרי *dinarei* to
gold דינרי *dinarei* because gold דינרי *dinarei* is easier to transport, it’s
a lot more value. Okay, so can you go ahead and take
the, transfer the קדושה *kedusha* of the מעשר שני *Ma’aser Sheni* from
the silver דינר *dinar* to the gold דינר *dinar*? So the הלכה
*halacha* is you can transfer קדושת מעשר שני *kedushat Ma’aser Sheni* from
fruit to currency, but not from currency to fruit, or not from
currency to currency. Okay, so I can't transfer from this pile of
silver דינרי *dinarei* to another pile of silver דינרי *dinarei*. But I
can go from fruit to silver. Can I go from silver to
gold? Well, this is exactly the question of our משנה *mishna*. When
you put the two of them together and you're talking about relative
to one another, one is פירות peirot, *peirot* and one is כסף
*kessef*. So which is which? So בית שמאי אומרים *Beit Shammai omrim*,
לא יעשה אדם סלעים דינרי זהב *Lo ya’aseh adam sla’im dinarei zahav*.
You can't swap the silver for gold, because presumably gold is the
כסף *kessef*, and silver, I'm sorry, no, excuse me, the silver is
the currency and the gold is the פירות peirot, *peirot*. And therefore
you can only go from fruit to כסף *kessef* and not the
reverse. בית הלל מתירים *Beit Hillel matirin*, בית הלל *Beit Hillel* allows
it. And so רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש *Rabbi Yochanan ve-Reish Lakish*, חד
אמר מחלוקת בסלעים על דינרים *Chad amar machloket besla’im al dinarim*. That
the debate is about from silver to gold. דבית שמאי סברי כספא
טיבעא *De-Beit Shammai savri kaspa tiva*,
that the silver is the currency, ודהבא פירא *ve-dahava peira*, and gold
is fruit. וטיבעא אפירא לא מחללינן *Ve-tiva apeira lo mechalelinan*, and you
can't go from currency to fruit. ובית הלל סברי כספא פירא ודהבא
טיבעא *U-Veit Hillel savri kaspa peira ve-dahava tiva*. It's the opposite. דהא
בי רב ורבי בזיקנותו *De-ha bi Rav ve-Rebbe be-ziknuto*. The silver is
the fruit, the gold is the currency, ופירא אטיבעא מחללינן *U-peira ativa
mechalelinan*, and you can go from the silver to the gold, from
fruit to currency. אבל פירות peirot על דינרים *Aval peirot al dinarim*,
but if you want to go straight from fruit to gold, דברי
הכל מחללין *divrei hakol mechalelin*, then everybody would say that's fine, because
it's not like gold isn't currency at all. The question is, is
gold currency vis-a-vis silver? Right? This is basically our משנה *mishna*. But
gold vis-a-vis real fruit, of course gold is currency and everybody would
say that's okay. מאי טעמא *Mai ta’ama*? מידי דהוה אכסף לבית הלל
*Midi de-hava
a-kessef le-Veit Hillel*. The same way silver works for בית הלל *Beit
Hillel*. כסף לבית הלל *Kessef le-Veit Hillel*, when you're dealing with silver
coins for בית הלל *Beit Hillel*, אף על גב דכספא לגבי דהבא
פירא הוי *af al gav de-kaspa legabei dahava peira havei*, even though
you're going from silver to gold, silver is considered the fruit, ברם
לגבי פירות טיבעא הוי *beram legabei peirot tiva havei*, but you can
be מחלל *mechalel* your fruit onto silver coins. I mean, that's how
this whole case began, that you had silver coins. So silver can
be currency for fruit and fruit for gold. Everybody, you with me
here? It's just like our משנה *mishna*. Okay. So זהב נמי לבית
שמאי *Zahav nami le-Beit Shammai*. So for בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* as
well, אף על גב דדהבא לגבי כספא פירא הוי *af al gav
de-dahava legabei kaspa peira havei*, even though they say you can't go
from gold to silver, because gold is, I'm sorry, you can't go
from silver to gold because gold is fruit in that scenario when
it's silver and gold combined, gold is fruit, so you can't go
from silver to gold, לגבי פירות טיבעא הוי *legabei peirot tiva havei*,
but if you're dealing with real fruit and gold, you can transfer
it. Okay, so this is like straight our משנה *mishna*. When you're
dealing with something that, you know, it's a relative determination. Everybody agrees
that all these currencies are currency vis-a-vis real fruit. The question is
gold and silver, which is the currency and which is the fruit?
Okay, בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* says that you go, that the silver
is the currency and you can't go from silver to gold. And
בית הלל *Beit Hillel* says in that case gold would be the
currency and you can go from silver to gold. Okay, so that's
and let's just read one more line of framing this. And the
גמרא says like this:
Okay, וחד אמר, v'chad amar, that was one of the positions of
רבי יוחנן ריש לקיש. Rabbi Yochanan Resh Lakish. But the other position
said, דפירות על גבי פירות על דינרים מחלוקת. d'peirot al gabey peirot
al dinarim machlokes. No, there's even a question if you can go
from straight fruit to gold. Gold might always be like, you know,
might never be currency, even relative to actual פירות, which you can
sort of understand. Like you know, if right now you wanted to
buy a gold coin, you'd go to some coin shop and you'd
buy some gold Krugerrands, right? In a certain place gold might in
theory be a standard, but no real person uses gold. So here
the argument could be that even vis-a-vis פירות, gold would be considered
more פירות and would not be considered currency. Okay, so that is
like a new question that we're asking. Okay, דהוי לגבי פירות טבע,
d'havay legabey peirot teva, וחד אמר אף פירות על דינרים. v'chad amar
af peirot al dinarim. Did we just finish that? דהוי לגבי פירות
טבע, d'havay legabey peirot teva, fine. וחד אמר אף על דינרים מחלוקת.
v'chad amar af al dinarim machlokes. Okay,
so fine, we'll end there, we'll pick up with that tomorrow.